Guide to the Katharine Byrd and Robert G. Breyer Family Papers on Richard E. Byrd, 1938-2007 SPEC.PA.56.0221
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
Katharine Byrd and Robert G. Breyer Family Papers on Richard E. Byrd
1938-2007
SPEC.PA.56.0221
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
1.26 Cubic feet
Richard E. Byrd was an Admiral of the United States Navy and polar explorer who led or participated in five expeditions to Antarctica between 1928 and 1956. He has been memorialized posthumously by numerous public and private entities around the world, including through building and monument dedications. One of Byrd's memorials was dedicated in 1962, in Wellington, New Zealand, to honor his contributions to exploration and international relations. Byrd's daughter and son-in-law, Katharine and Robert, participated in many programs honoring Byrd in the decades after his death. The Katharine Byrd and Robert G. Breyer Family Papers on Richard E. Byrd contain correspondence, clippings, photographs, programs, and other documents related to Katharine Byrd and Robert Breyer's involvement in Richard E. Byrd's legacy. The collection also contains clippings reflecting on the contributions of Richard E. Byrd, correspondence and clippings from or regarding polar explorers that worked with Byrd, and a few items dated before Richard E. Byrd's death, including some correspondence from Byrd. The materials are dated 1938-2007.
(1) 5" letter document box; (1) 2.5" letter document box; (1) flat box; (1) oversize flat box
Breyer, Katharine Byrd
Breyer, Robert Byrd
Breyer, Robert G.
Arrangement of Materials
This collection is arranged chronologically, and alphabetically by topic or given title within the same date.
Acquisitions Information
Accession No. PA.2018.0013: Robert Breyer, 2016 March
Access to Materials
This collection is available for patron research, but may be used in the University Archives reading room only. Audio/visual materials and computer media may need a use copy produced before access is allowed. Contact the Byrd Polar and Climate Research Center Archival Program at polararchives@osu.edu for more information.
Biographical Note
Richard E. Byrd (1888-1957) was an Admiral of the United States Navy and polar explorer who led or participated in five expeditions to Antarctica between 1928 and 1956. He has been memorialized posthumously by numerous public and private entities around the world through building and monument dedications, medals, postage stamps, portraits, United States ship names, and various other awards and honors. Byrd has two memorials in New Zealand, one of which was dedicated on March 11, 1962, on the fifth anniversary of his death. The bronze bust was dedicated in Wellington, New Zealand, honoring Byrd's contributions to exploration and international relations. New Zealand had been used historically as a departure point for Byrd's expeditions. Richard E. Byrd married Marie Donaldson Ames in 1915. Katharine Byrd Breyer (1924-1999) was one of their four children. She married Robert G. Breyer (1918-1980), and the couple participated in many programs memorializing Admiral Byrd in the decades after his death. Katharine actively sought to preserve her father's legacy throughout her life. Katharine and Robert's son, Robert Byrd Breyer, was a resident of Los Angeles, California, as of 2018.
Scope and Contents
The Katharine Byrd and Robert G. Breyer Family Papers on Richard E. Byrd contain correspondence, a plaque, a scrapbook, clippings, photographs, programs, and other documents related to Katharine Byrd Breyer and her husband Robert G. Breyer's participation in programs honoring Katharine's father, Admiral Richard E. Byrd. The materials mainly relate to posthumous building, ship, and monument dedications, and other ceremonies honoring Richard E. Byrd from locations around the world, including a significant dedication in Wellington, New Zealand, on the fifth anniversary of Byrd's death in 1962. The collection also contains clippings reflecting on the life and contributions of Richard E. Byrd, correspondence and clippings from or regarding polar explorers that worked with Byrd, and some general correspondence Katharine and Robert G. sent regarding Richard E. Byrd's legacy and archives. The collection also has a few items dated before Richard E. Byrd's death, including some correspondence sent from Byrd to Katharine and Robert, and one 2007 clipping on Richard E. Byrd collected by Robert G. and Katharine's son, Robert Byrd Breyer. The materials are dated 1938-2007.
Breyer, Katharine Byrd; Breyer, Robert G.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957--Monuments; Antarctica--Discovery and exploration--American--20th century; Dedication services--20th century; Explorers--Press coverage--20th century; Explorers--United States--20th century; Families of military personnel--United States--20th century; Monuments--20th century; Monuments--New Zealand--Wellington (Region)--Wellington--20th century
- "Courage: A Tribute to Rear Admiral Richard E. Byrd" memorial booklet signed by Jim Mooney, addressed to "Kay Byrd Breyer", 1938 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Byrd (Richard E.) correspondence sent to Katharine Byrd from Japan in WWII, 1945 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Byrd (Richard E.) correspondence sent to Robert G. Breyer, 1950 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings regarding Richard E. Byrd, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Byrd (Richard E.) empty envelope sent to Katharine and Robert G. Breyer, circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "U.S. Breaks Into a Frozen Continent" in Life, circa 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "City Honors Adm. Byrd, Eisenhower Sends Greetings" Herald Tribune clipping, 1956 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Martin (David) correspondence sent to Robert G. Breyer regarding Wisdom Award given to Richard E. Byrd, 1956 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
- New York Times clippings and Richard E. Byrd and Bud Waite photograph sent to Breyer family by Bud Waite, 1956, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Breyer (Katharine Byrd) correspondence sent to Robert G. Bryer regarding health of Richard E. Byrd, 1957 March (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "L.A. Veterans Pay Tribute to Adm. Byrd" Los Angeles Times, 1957 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Expeditions Led by Adm. Byrd Tore the Veil from Half of America" clipping and color map, circa 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Farmers and Merchants National Bank branch dedication photographs, invitation, correspondence and clippings, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- S.J. (Senate Joint) Res. (Resolution) 103 to authorize Richard E. Byrd statue in Virginia, 1959 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Mount Victoria, Wellington New Zealand memorial gatherings photographs and personal tributes, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- USS (United State Ship) Richard E. Byrd (DDG-23) launching, invitations, programs and correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Admiral Byrd Memorial Unveiled" in The Weekly News, 1962 March 21 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "Bust of an Admiral" in The Weekly News, 1962 March 21 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Mount Victoria, Wellington Byrd Memorial photographs, program, and correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Missile Destroyer Commissioned" Seattle Post-Intelligencer clipping, 1964 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Richard E. Byrd Memorial Mount Victoria invitation, 1964 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Dedication of Executive Offices, Greenwich, Connecticut program, 1964 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Anniversary of Polar Flight" Christian Science Monitor clipping, 1967 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "Byrd Polar Ship, Old North Star, Being Overhauled" Los Angeles Times clipping, 1968 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- International Aerospace Hall of Fame Award of Honor to Admiral Byrd plaque, 1968 September 7 (Box 4)
- International Aerospace Hall of Fame Awards Banquet scrapbook, 1968 September (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "Study Supports Byrd's Polar Flight Story" Los Angeles Times clipping, 1973 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Pete" Demas Los Angeles Times obituary, 1979 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Roos (Eddie) correspondence sent to Robert G. Breyer with photographs, 1981 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Waite (Bud) correspondence to Breyer family in support of Richard E. Byrd (photocopy) 1984, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Face of Antarctic Explorer on New Stamp" The Winchester Star clipping, 1988 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Roosevelt (Franklin D.) correspondence with Richard E. Byrd (photocopy) 1940 September 19, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence and press releases regarding the honoring of Richard E. Byrd and the Antarctic Treaty, 1940, 1956 (photocopies), circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Hero Foundation and various government agencies correspondence with Katharine Byrd Breyer regarding a merchant mariner memorial, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Mount Victoria, Wellington Byrd Memorial restoration correspondence and clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Richard E. Byrd Building dedicated at Shearwater, Nova Scotia, photographs and public affairs correspondence, 1995 April-November (Box 1, Folder 31)
- North (Andrew) correspondence sent to Katharine Byrd Breyer, 1996 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- "Exploring the Far Reaches: Remembering Admiral Byrd" in The Kappa Alpha Journal, 1996 Summer (Box 1, Folder 33)
- "Antarctic Flashback: Byrd's Second Expedition" in Antarctic, 1997 March (Box 2, Folder 1)
- National Archives correspondence sent to Katharine Byrd Breyer regarding Richard E. Byrd films, 1997 July 14 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Scientists Extend New Appreciation for Byrd's Legacy" The Winchester Star clipping, 1997 July 14 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Statue dedication in Winchester, Virginia program and invitation, 1997 July 14 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Winchester, Virginia Richard E. Byrd bronze statue unveiling clippings, 1997 July 15 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- United States Postal Service announcement of Teterboro Hall of Fame and Museum grand opening, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "Admiral is Placed on a New Pedestal" The Winchester Star clipping, 1999 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "The Admiral's Quarters" Boston Sunday Globe clipping, 2007 February 18 (Box 2, Folder 7)